In these mountains,
live the strange people.
They have been protected and isolated
from the rest of the world for centuries.
Grand Dragon is their medicine man,
their seer.
He knows all and he spoke to us.
Two thousand years ago,
two tribes arrived here.
They were the Yi
who were fleeing the Sichuan province
and the Hani from Tibet.
Defying the steep slopes with buffaloes,
they worked the mountains
and invented the irrigated rice terrace.
The Chinese emperor rewarded them
and baptized them The Mountain Sculptors.
[Hani spoken audio]
So that everyone has a rice paddy,
the Hani and the Yi
sculpt their mountains each year.
However, to change the land,
they need the approval
of the natural forces.
Therefore, they appeal to Grand Dragon
for he alone has the power
to question the wind,
the rain and the seasons,
and to choose the best time
to sculpt the new mountain.
[Hani spoken audio].
Twenty centuries were required
to shape this land.
The people here like to admire it.
Their past is engraved in these mountains.
This tremendous work
would never have been possible
without the help of the buffalo.
To work the land and move boulders
for growing rice and for carrying men,
the buffalo has always been there,
as strong as a mountain
and as serene as a rice paddies water.
Every man is connected
to a buffalo for life.
When he dies,
his buffalo is buried with him.
Grand Dragon's buffalo
is called Immense Knowledge.
You never see the one without the other,
but Immense Knowledge
isn't just an ordinary buffalo.
He is the messenger
of the natural spirits.
Grand Dragon watches the movement
of his eyes, his ears,
and the way his horns
rock from side to side.
He reads through hoofprints
that Immense Knowledge leaves behind him.
There have been seers, from father to son,
in Grand Dragon's family
for 58 generations,
and always with the same buffalos.
Rice is the center of the Hani's life.
Every family owns about 100 small plots
within a radius
of nine miles of the village.
Usually, they are passed down
through the family.
Sometimes they lose track
of who owns what,
so they come to Grand Dragon.
The paddies are watched constantly,
they must never dry up.
In one year alone,
they are plowed five times
and raked four times.
The right moment has to be chosen.
For that, they always ask
for Grand Dragon's advice.
He has to climb up to some paddies
and down to others.
He listens and advises.
Some evenings,
his legs are numb from fatigue.
Below in the valley,
part of the harvest is used for barter.
The rest feeds the people.
Depending on the altitude,
the quality of the soil,
and the exposure to the sun,
13 varieties of rice are grown,
three of which are the sticky variety.
They are always afraid
of making a mistake,
so they ask Grand Dragon, of course.
[Hani spoken audio].
There are never any windows
in the dwellings.
The smoke is supposed to stay inside.
It keeps insects and rodents away
and protects the rice stored in the lofts.
Grand Dragon has asked the wind,
the clouds and the springs.
The Yellow Mountain
must be sculpted at the next moon.
He must now begin
preparing the major project.
His mission begins tomorrow.
[Hani spoken audio].
To begin with, water has to be found.
In this area,
springs are found on mountaintops.
The waterkeeper protects the springs.
She alone knows
the underground pathways of the water
for irrigating the new mountain.
[Hani spoken audio].
A buffalo's hide is fragile.
It must always be kept damp.
Otherwise, it cracks
and the buffalo goes crazy.
[Hani spoken audio]
Next, Grand Dragon has to convince
the Yi tribe to take part in the work.
According to ritual,
he visits Old Tiger, the Yi's sorcerer.
[Hani spoken audio].
The Yellow Mountain will be sculpted
halfway up the northern slope,
which makes it midway
between the two villages.
[Hani spoken audio].
The Hanis and the Yis
use the mountain echoes
to spread the news.
In a few hours,
all the villagers will know
where and when the work is to begin.
[Hani spoken audio].
The time has come for Grand Dragon
to withdraw and consult his ancestors,
and go back in time
to the very first sorcerer
to remember the first mountain
and call up the strength
that led to it being sculpted.
Meanwhile, another Grand Dragon
takes his place in the village.
The great day arrives.
Grand Dragon expels the evil spirits.
The village has to be cleaned.
Evil spirits have infiltrated everywhere,
the streets and the lofts.
They must be chased away.
[Hani spoken audio].
The Yi consider that vivid colors
suit their women best.
As for the Hani,
they think their women
are too beautiful already,
so they dress them in dark colors.
For the great day,
they forget their differences
and like the very first time,
sculpt the mountains together.
So goes the tradition.
[Hani spoken audio].
The new rice paddies
will be shared by the two communities.
The Feast of the Long Table
signals the beginning
of a new monsoon season.
It will be followed by other ceremonies.
The awakening of the insects,
the swings, the new rice,
and each time,
Grand Dragon will have to say
what there is to do
and when it must be done.
Mountain Sculptors are like that.
They love celebrations and rice alcohol.
[Hani spoken audio].
Grand Dragon's mission is nearly over.
Now, he must thank the forces of nature,
those that will protect
the Yellow Mountain.
For that, he has to plow 12 rice paddies
with his buffalo, Immense Knowledge.
Twelve paddies are offered to nature.
One for the wind,
one for the mountain,
one for the clouds,
one for the springs…
The day will come when Grand Dragon's son
will take his place.
As ever, it will be his job
to protect the mountains and rice paddies.
[Hani spoken audio].